[Music]
Welcome to what's new and financial
reporting for authors in uh the 2025
release wave one for Business Central.
In this session, I'm going to show you
the new things that you get, new tools,
internal descriptions, intro and closing
paragraphs, some new things in row
definitions, and some new things in
column definitions. So let's dive into
Business Central and uh author some
reports. We get to financial reporting
from many places. I'll choose financial
reporting from the RO center. And you
notice already here that the report
definition has this internal
description. And we change the display
title to be display title, the caption
and not description because this is
really the title of the report. So let's
dive into the income statement and edit
report definition here and see what new
things we have. First of all, we moved
the title up here so you get a little
bit of more um screen size
there. You also have uh new options here
under definitions. You can edit the
introductory and closing paragraphs. So
for this report the author has put in
something about a preliminary edition
and that this report is being audited
but you can put in any text you like.
When any user run the report this will
come as a closing and end paragraph. You
can see that in the user video if you're
interested. Here is also where you
change the internal description for for
the report. So maybe this is where you
document your report definition uh in
case you need to go back and and kind of
check uh what's
cooking. Um there's a new negative
amount format here. So you can change
that for the report either use
parentheses or minus. So you can see
that changing here that is also
reflected in the PDF version. And um
there's also a new thing where we have
support for Excel layouts. Um so here
under export to Excel sorry is
definitions you can define a number of
Excel layouts choose which one is the
default one and then that's how users
can consume your layouts. All of this is
demoed in the user video. So go check
that out there.
Let me go back to the list here and uh
just quickly show you in if you have
haven't noticed this menu from last wave
the copy export import. I'll just copy
this report definition. You'll notice
why in a sec. Let me just call that uh
income 2. And uh so now I took a copy of
that. So back here I can now see my
income 2 income statement. And that's a
copy.
Great. Let's dive into the row
definition uh first of this income
statement. And I'll just uh simply go
navigate
here. And
um just for report definitions, the
column definitions now have the ability
for you to document them with an
internal description. And there's also
uh something um a new thing here a new
action called where used. So imagine
that you might want to change a row
definition but you are uncertain on the
impact of this change because this row
definition could be used in multiple
reports. So the where used action both
here on the list and also in edit mode.
um I can simply check that this
particular row definition is being used
for these two reports which is also why
I wanted to do that copy for you. So
that's uh nice to know even before you
get started. Let me go and actually edit
the row
definition. Uh this is fine. No, I do
not want to do that. Here we go. So
um income statement edit row definition.
No, I don't want to make a copy. I just
want to go in. So again the the where
used is shown here directly in edit mode
as well. A new thing on this page is
that the double underline option is now
not hidden anymore. It's been there
forever but uh but somehow we got that
hidden so it's not now you can you can
use it everywhere.
If you are in doubt about what's the
like meaning of all these different
things, when do I use show if any and so
on. By the way, this is if you use this
show um and only show the row when when
any of the columns are non zero. This is
uh what will then be shown on the report
um if people toggle uh the the show
empty rows both now on the view mode and
also in the PDF. But if you're in doubt
of what all these mean, there's help to
get. Let me just open the help pane
here. And uh this immediately show you a
little bit about what this is, but also
points to a new documentation page that
we added to the financial reporting uh
documentation on row definitions. Let me
just open this. And um here you now get
a lot more advice on working with row
formulas uh how to format uh how to add
empty lines and conditional formatting
and so on. So if you're in doubt about
how to use financial reporting row
definitions, go check out the
documentation. I'll just close the help
and go back to my overview here and go
back to the to the report definitions.
And now dive into columns. Again in
column definitions we have added this
internal description and there's all the
same kind of where used action. So you
can also see where a particular column
definition is being used. But in here I
just want to edit the column definition
and show you a new kit on the block for
column type. Um so you have been able to
do year-to- date for many years but now
as a new thing in this wave we also
added the monthto date. So uh so that's
a new option that you can use in your
column
definitions. Again if you if you want to
know more about column definitions just
choose the help here and there's
directly the link for how to work with
column definitions in your financial
reporting. So that's it for the report
author. I hope that you will um do a lot
of good reports for your users and
hopefully dive in to the Excel layout as
well, which is a new promising feature
where we make it even easier to use
Excel with your financial statements.